KEVIN MARAGA

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Name: Kevin Maraga, Contacts: P.O Box 581, Kitale.

Tel: 0714678603,

Email.Kmaraga8882@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Kevin has acquired wide experience in project Monitoring & Evaluation involving database design & management, Monitoring and Evaluation (Development of M&E frameworks, Performance Monitoring Plans, Activity M&E plans) and Analysis in Socio-Economic, Agriculture and Health Research. Excellent proficiency in STATA, R,C, C++, Cspro ,N-VIVO, SAS, SPSS programming. Able to apply advanced Statistical/Econometric techniques in the design, implementation and analysis of Time series, Survival, Longitudinal, Multilevel, Population Surveys, Randomized Controlled Trials and other study designs. He is proficient in analyzing large quantitative & qualitative datasets derived from Case studies, Surveys and experiments. He has a practical experience in developing questionnaires, data collection, data entry and report writing using Microsoft office and analysis using various statistical packages. He has intense interests in project management, youth, gender mainstreaming, grant management, conflict resolution, governance, nutrition, environmental conservation, agricultural and rural development issues in Africa

CAREER OBJECTIVES

- To secure a job assignment where my existing skills in various fields can be utilized.
- To be participant in growth and success process of an organization.
- To be a team player in a team that enhances timely and quality service delivery

HIGHLIGHTS OF RECENT ASSIGNMENTS

In recently successfully managed Baseline survey for our CDP-3 program in Rwanda and remotely facilitated training of our internal data collection system for our field team in Malawi and Mozambique. I have also supported/supervise two of our programs in Kenya successful conduct data quality audit.

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

2015-2017 University of Nairobi

MSc. Social Statistics (Ongoing)

2008 to 2012 MOI University

BSc. Applied Statistics With Computing

2003-2006 St. Joseph's Boys' High School,

Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education [K.C.S.E]

[Mean grade B+]

Additional professional qualification

- 1. Introduction class on development evaluation
- 2. Equity-focus evaluation
- 3. Emerging practices in development
- 4. National evaluation capacity development for county led M&E system
- 5. Age, Gender and Diversity Approach
- 6. Essential Skills for New Managers
- 7. M&E Fundamentals
- 8. Computer literacy: MS Office applications, Arc View and MS Project Professional

- 9. Statistical Packages; SPSS.R, SAS, STATA, CSPro, Epi Info, Matlab.
- 10. Guidance and Counseling.
- 11. Community Health Worker.

Memberships

- Member, American Evaluation Association
- African Evaluation Association

WORKSHOPS AND SEMINAR

- Inside NGO: United States Agency for International Development Rules and Regulations Training: Grants and cooperative Agreements
- Developing Monitoring and Evaluation Frameworks(AEA Conference)
- Meta-analysis(AEA Conference)
- Basics of Program Design: A Theory-Driven Approach(AEA Conference)
- Engaging Participants in the Evaluation Process: A Participatory Approach(AEA Conference)
- Propensity Score Matching: Theories and Applications(AEA Conference)
- Applications of Power Analysis in the Designs of Multilevel Experimental and Quasi Experimental Evaluations(AEA Conference)
- Mixed Methods in International Development: Just a fad or a reasonable strategy to enhance the quality of Performance and Impact Evaluation(AEA Conference)
- Participatory Action Evaluation -- Emergent method of evaluation(AEA Conference)
- Employment and Investment Opportunities, Business Processes Outsourcing and Ethics at the Work Place.
- Travel Safety and Personal Security
- Humanitarianism, (Applying Key Principles)

Languages Well versed in both spoken and written English, Kiswahili

Personal Attributes, Key Competencies And Skills:

Highly disciplined with high levels of integrity, Proactive, self-driven, diligent and highly flexible, Possesses a greater attention to detail, A strong believer in teamwork synergy, A believer in winning with integrity, A fast learner and a proven ability to multitask. Courteous and trustworthy, ability to work under pressure and meet strict deadlines with minimum supervision, good communication, interpersonal and analytical skills very flexible and versatile.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2014 Feb to Date: Global Monitoring & Evaluation Associate (land o' lakes) Based in Nairobi Regional Office; supporting global projects. Key roles included supporting Monitoring and Evaluation efforts for Land O'Lakes worldwide development programs in Africa

- Support M&E efforts at project design/proposal stage, start-ups, baselines assessments, on-going monitoring activities and reporting, evaluations (Midterm and final), close-outs, reports and final documentation
- Support in drafting project Performance Management Plans (PMPs)/ Performance Monitoring and Evaluation Plan (PMEP)
- Develop data quality Assessment tools and guidelines.
- Support in completing data quality management forms for individual projects based on PMP guidelines
- Support in designing data entry templates and data analysis for projects.
- Support in drafting data collection tools, including monitoring tools for projects
- Support in collection of Practice Area Indicators (PAIs) on a quarterly basis
- Analysis of selected Divisional Impact Indicators (DII)
- Assist in preparation/Review progress reports and scope of works.
- Support recruitment and training of local/country M&E teams

- Documentation of lesson learned, organizing and co-facilitate learning events.
- Coordinate with other teams from headquarters to ensure that set standards are adhered to in key processes and systems.
- Design and carry out surveys and assessments
- Any other related tasks and responsibilities that may be required.

Some of the projects I supported in role include:

- The Kenya Semi-Arid Livestock Enhancement Support (K-SALES) Project 2013 2017: A three year meat value chain project that aim to address problems Agro-pastoralists living in the Semi-Arid Zone 2 (SA2) of Kenya face unreliable access to water, cyclical drought, high prevalence of livestock diseases and limited inputs and services. The project directly benefits livestock producers and private business service providers (BSPs) through the development of a fully-functioning, inclusive livestock value chain. K-SALES work along the live animal, meat, and hides/skins value-chains for cattle and shoats in six counties of Kenya.
- Cooperative Development Project (CDP) (2012- 2018): The Cooperative Development Program aims to increase access to self-reliant cooperative enterprises that meet the evolving needs of their members and contribute to improved quality of life for members, especially women, through the formation and increased competitiveness of self-sustaining horizontally and/or vertically integrated dairy cooperatives. The project is implemented in five countries Kenya, Uganda, Rwanda, Ethiopia and Tanzania
- Malawi Food for Progress (2014-16): Project goal was to increase key crop production, strengthen farmer organizations and market linkages, and improve the effectiveness of government and other service providers in transitioning agriculture towards market-oriented farming to increase household incomes. The project works in three value chains Cassava, Rice and small livestock.
- Feed the Future Kenya Innovation Engine (KIE) (2013-2017): KIE is intended to harness the power of innovative private sector approaches to leverage resources and integrate new approaches to agricultural solutions, thereby accelerating efforts to address poverty and food security needs in Kenya.
- Tanzania Innovations in Gender Equality (USAID Washington) (2014-2017): The USAID funded project is implementing a set of activities that aim to advance women's leadership in agriculture.
- Powering African Agriculture-PAA(2010- 2014) .The USAID funded project will contribute to USAID Feed the Future and Global Climate Change objectives by helping to identify, commercialize and bring to scale innovative clean energy solutions for cutting edge agricultural applications in Sub-Saharan Africa. By providing on-demand analytic support to AFR/SD and building the capacity of Energy Grand Challenge grantees, we will ensure that clean energy technologies are leveraged to increase agricultural productivity and competiveness in ways that improve household incomes and food security.
- Ethiopia -Empowering New Generations to Improve Nutrition and Economic opportunities (ENGINE)" program is primed by SAVE with Land O' Lakes as a sub leading economic strengthening activities and improving small scale production for crops and livestock.
- Kenya Aphia+ IMARISHA KAI (2012-2016). The purpose of the Project is to design a health service delivery program that responds to the Results as outlined in the USAID/Kenya Implementation Framework (20 I 0-2015), whose strategic goal is "health outcomes and impact through sustainable country-led programs and partnerships." The two-pronged approach seeks to provide support to service delivery and strengthen health systems.

2013 May to Aug: M & E Assistant (Mercy Corps)

• Assist M&E specialist to carry out assessments of youth and youth groups' economic situations before and after financial literacy trainings within the affected communities and make

recommendations for actions that are consistent with program objectives.

- Train program TOTs and local partners on financial literacy, logical framework, data management, data analysis and results-oriented programming, basic surveying and sampling techniques, monitoring and evaluation methods and principles, report writing techniques and requirements for Mercy Corps.
- Implement and improve existing monitoring and assessment tools for the involved youth groups to ensure the appropriateness of the program and to gauge its impact, including a system of recording and presenting relevant data.
- Assist the M&E Specialist assess, and conduct final survey/assessment to measure the financial education outcomes Provide reporting including contributions to regular conflicts reports, as well as more general situation reports.
- Prepare other documentation and write success stories for internal Mercy Corps use and external requirements as may be required. Travel to the field to monitor and evaluate project sites, work with beneficiary groups, and organize and conduct assessments as necessary.
- Assist in Ensure that program activities are implemented according to the implementation plan and in an efficient and effective manner.
- Play a key role in the development of systems and mechanisms to ensure the successful implementation of the program; including submission of quality weekly updates, and ensuring that program progress tracking records are kept up to date. Write reports and document work carried out in the field.
- Assist the Monitoring and Evaluation Officer, conduct pre-monitoring visits to assess the suitability of proposed projects and conduct assessments of partners.
- Provide follow up recommendations and solutions where there are problems in implementation. Liaise with other NGOs and government officers to help resolve problems in the field other duties as assigned.

2013 February-April 2013: Data Officer (Mercy Corps)

- Assisting in the revision and improvement of M&E data collection tools to ensure accuracy in data collection, lead data collection and entry together with LEAP, YYC and WU field teams,
- Ensuring that program data from field sites has been verified and entered in the respective programmatic databases in a timely manner, correctly and accurately ready for analysis and reports generation,
- Lead in data cleaning, aggregation and basic data analysis as directed by the M&E Specialist, together with the M&E specialist develop data or research ownership and protocol documents for both internal and external project teams.
- Assists the Monitoring and Evaluation Officer, conduct monitoring visits to assess the progress and effectiveness of community projects supported by Mercy Corps.
- Maintaining all programs data base for information extraction when required and other duties as may be assigned by the M&E Specialist.

2012 November –January 2013 Job Position: Voter Registration Clerk

Worked as voter registration and verification clerk for IEBC in Saboti constituency.

2012 September Job Position: Data Clerk

Involved in data collection, data entry using CSPro and data cleaning for Mercy Corps in Eldoret.

2012 May – September Job Position: Community Health Worker officer (ministry of health)

- Designing and implementing tools for data collection, entry, and analysis using SPSS and STATA programs and reporting of research findings.
- Leadership of the recruitment, selection and training of field graduate interns on tools developed for data collection; specifically taking a lead role in implementation of field related activities for the survey based approach.
- Educating and advising the local community on health related issues, carry out dialogue and action day.
- Supervise distribution of mosquito nets, ECD and water treatment materials.

2011 April-July Job Position: Industrial Attachment at Transnzoia County.

- Compilation and reconciliation of council's monthly reports.
- Assist preparing the proposed budget, assist in auditing revenue collection books.
- Updating the local authority integrated financial operation management system.
- Lead in identifying discrepancies existing in the payroll and the employees register, organizing updating and documentation of the employee's personal records.
- Preparing of tender documents, tender notice and procurement plan, preparing of quotations and memorandum of co-operation.

2009 August Job Position: Enumerator.

The Kenya population and housing census of 2009.

2007-2008 Job Position: Untrained Teacher.

Worked as untrained teacher at Nyabigena secondary school, teaching mathematics and physics.

REFEREES

Daniel A. Dianga, Monitoring & Evaluation Analyst, Land O' Lakes, Inc. | International development, Tel: +254(0)202327831|+254724234287

Cell +254722618432

Email: daniel.dianga@idd.landolakes.com

Richard Onyancha, Chief of Party LEAP, Mercy Corps, Nairobi. Tel 0725818975

Email: ronyancha@ke.mercycorps.org

Mrs. Edna Ogwangi

Director-Monitoring, Evaluation and Learning

E mail: Edna.Ogwangi@yahoo.com Skype: edna.ogwangi

Stop Hunger Now Tel: +16512309046

